Register of the David James Webster Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
David James Webster papers,
1989-2001
2004C5
Webster, David, 1931-
6 manuscript boxes (2.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, and memoranda, relating to post-communist era radio and television broadcasting in Eastern Europe.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2004.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1931 January 11 Born, Taunton, England
? Attended Taunton School and Ruskin College, Oxford
1953 Joined British Broadcasting Corporation in the World Services News Department
1958 Moved to British Broadcasting Corporation television
1967-1969 Editor, British Broadcasting Corporation television public program, Panorama
1970 Assistant Head of the Television Current Affairs Group
1971-1976 Representative of British Broadcasting Corporation in the United States
1974-1975 Chairman of the International Council of the National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences
1977-1981 Director of Public Affairs, British Broadcasting Corporation Member, Board of Management, British Broadcasting Corporation
1981-1985 Resident director, British Broadcasting Corporation in the United States while retaining his seat on the Management Board in England
1985-1987 Resident Associate, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace
1986 Returned to England to become Controller, Information Services and concurrently, Acting Secretary of the British Broadcasting Corporation
1987-1992 Senior Fellow, Annenberg Washington Program on Communication Policy Studies Director, Annenberg International Disaster Communications Project
1988- Founder and Chairman, Trans-Atlantic Dialogue on European Broadcasting
2003 August 6 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The David James Webster papers consist of correspondence, reports, and memoranda relating to post-communist era radio and television broadcasting in Eastern Europe. Webster created the Trans-Atlantic Dialogue on European Broadcasting in 1988 to realize his goal of introducing democratic ways of broadcasting in former Soviet bloc countries by helping them enact new legislation and establish new infrastructure with regulatory bodies. The papers are focused on Webster's activities with this organization, though some records of the Trans-Atlantic Dialogue on Broadcasting and the Information Society are also included.
Conferences, programs, seminars, symposiums, projects, and official missions to different countries were the tools Webster used to accomplish the goals of Trans-Atlantic Dialogue. Of these tools, the hypothetical seminars, based on role-playing and free and unscripted discussion by participants of issues involved in the democratization of broadcasting, are well documented in the TRANS-ATLANTIC DIALOGUE ON EUROPEAN BROADCASTING OFFICE FILE.
Of all the projects undertaken by Webster through Tran-Atlantic Dialogue, the Democracy Audit Project is particularly well documented in the papers. Its objective was to monitor the level of freedom, independence, and openness of the media, and the status of human rights. It was carried out by setting up local institutions whose role was to act as watchdogs.
Most of the financial support for Trans-Atlantic Dialogue was provided by the Phare and Tacis Democracy Programme, which was started by the European Union in 1992 to promote democracy in the former Soviet bloc countries through economic and political reforms. In addition to material in the TRANS- ATLANTIC DIALOGUE ON EUROPEAN BROADCASTING OFFICE FILE, this organization's activities are documented in files printed from the COMPUTER DISK.
Webster also had close contact with the Soros Foundation, which initiated and supported openness in society through independent organizations established in particular countries, such as Albania, Belarus, Crimea, and Croatia. Webster's relationship with this organization is documented in the SOROS FOUNDATION FILE.
The FILE ON ORGANIZATIONS relates to the activities of various organizations promoting democracy and human rights, the situation in Macedonia, and the development of independent media.
The David Webster papers were acquired in 2003.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Trans-Atlantic Dialogue on European Broadcasting (Organization); Radio broadcasting--Europe, Eastern.; Television broadcasting--Europe, Eastern.
Collection Contents
- Trans-Atlantic Dialogue on European Broadcasting Office File, 1989-2001. (Box 1-4)
  Appointment calendars; conference, seminar, symposium, and workshop material; correspondence; financial records; lists; memoranda; minutes of meetings; program file; proposals; reports; speeches and writings; and travel file relating to the organization's efforts under the chairmanship of David Webster to promote democratic ways of radio and television broadcasting in the former Soviet bloc, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Appointment calendars, 1990-1991. (Folder 1: 1)
  - Conference, seminar, symposium, and workshop material.
    Includes related correspondence, memoranda, and other materials
    - General, 1992-1994. (Folder 1: 2)
    - Human Dimension Seminar, the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe (CSCE), Office for Democratic Institutions and Human Rights (ODHIR), Warsaw, Poland, 1993 November. (Folder 1: 3)
    - Symposium, "Government and Broadcasting," Bulgaria and Romania, 1994 March. (Folder 1: 4)
    - Workshops, Bratislava and Prague, 1994 April. (Folder 1: 5)
    - Budapest Review Conference, 1994 June-July. (Folder 1: 6)
    - Hypothetical seminars in Hungary and Poland on the "Relations between the Government and the Media," 1994 September 12-16. (Folder 1: 7)
    - Hypothetical seminars in Hungary and Poland on the "Relations between the Government and the Media," 1994 September 12-16. (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Correspondence.
    Includes letters neither from nor to David Webster
    - General, 1990-1994. (Folder 2: 2)
    - AMWAB, 1993. (Folder 2: 3)
    - Beaird, Richard C., 1992. (Folder 2: 4)
    - Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1991-1992. (Folder 2: 5)
    - Center for the Study of Democracy, 1993. (Folder 2: 6)
    - Eberhardt, Eva, 1993-1995. (Folder 2: 7)
    - Harartzi, Miklos, n.d. (Folder 2: 8)
    - Jarrett, Bob, 1994. (Folder 2: 9)
    - Lake, Anthony, 1994. (Folder 2: 10)
    - Mosher, Fritz, 1992. (Folder 2: 11)
    - Pralong, Sandra, 1995. (Folder 2: 12)
      Includes memoranda and travel schedule
    - Price, Gareth, n.d. (Folder 2: 13)
    - Schmidt-Montfort, Sonja, 1994. (Folder 2: 14)
    - Talbott, Strobe, 1994. (Folder 2: 15)
    - Willard, Richard, 1995. (Folder 2: 16)
  - Financial records.
    Includes contracts, grant agreements, and related materials
    - General, 1994. (Folder 2: 17)
    - Commission of the European Communities (CEC), 1996. (Folder 2: 18)
    - International Media Fund, 1990-1991. (Folder 2: 19)
    - Markle Foundation, 1992. (Folder 2: 20)
    - National Endowment for Democracy, 1990-1995. (Folder 2: 21-22)
  - Lists, n.d. (Folder 2: 23)
  - Memoranda, 1992-1995. (Folder 2: 24)
    Includes memoranda neither to nor from David Webster
  - Minutes of meetings, 1992-2001. (Folder 2: 25)
    British Broadcasting Corporation, London, 1992 May 19-20; Regulatory meeting, Prague, Czech Republic, 1994 December 5; Meeting on "Criminality and Control in the Digital World," The Hague, 1997 June 6-8; and Office of the Prime Minister, Sweden, 2001 July 6-7
  - Program file
    - Annenberg Washington Program in Communications Policy Studies of Northwestern University and the Trans-Atlantic Dialogue on European Broadcasting joint project on "Building Democracy: New Broadcasting Laws in East and Central Europe," n.d. (Folder 3: 1)
      Report prepared by David Webster
    - Media Program in Central and Eastern Europe (CEE), 1995. (Folder 3: 2)
    - Phare and Tacis Democracy Programme., See also box 6
      - Brochures, n.d. (Folder 3: 3)
      - Applications, 1992-1995. (Folder 3: 4-7)
        Includes related materials
      - Financial records, 1993-2000. (Folder 3: 8-9)
        Includes correspondence and other related materials
      - Letters, 1992-1995. (Folder 3: 10)
      - Memoranda, 1992-1994. (Box-folder 4: 1)
      - Note, 1992. (Folder 4: 2)
      - Organizational records, n.d. (Folder 4: 3)
      - Project file
        - Partner projects, 1994. (Folder 4: 4)
        - Phare Democracy Audit Project: Audit of the Media Legislation in East and Central Europe
          - General, 1995 June. (Folder 4: 5)
          - Application for funding, 1995 April. (Folder 4: 6)
          - Memoranda, 1994-1995. (Folder 4: 7)
      - Proposals, 1994. (Folder 4: 8)
      - Report on Phare Democracy Project Implementation, 1994. (Folder 4: 9)
  - Proposals, 1992-1995. (Folder 4: 10-11)
    Consists of proposals for European Satellite Consortium initiated by David Webster, and "Media Watch" for media monitoring in East and Central Europe, presented to OMRI in conjunction with Democracy Works
  - Reports, 1989-1994. (Folder 4: 12)
    Consists of report on the goals and accomplishments of Trans-Atlantic Dialogue and report on Albanian visit by Daniel Brenner
  - Speeches and writings
    - Testimony by David Webster, Subcommittee on Telecommunications and Finance, U.S. House of Representatives, 1989 July 26. (Folder 4: 13)
      Typescript
    - "Broadcasting in Europe and America: The Old Order Passeth," remarks, Belgium, 1991 April 11. (Folder 4: 14)
    - Building Free and Independent Media, Freedom Paper Series, 1992 August. (Folder 4: 15)
      Printed copy
  - Travel file, 1990-1995. (Folder 4: 16)
- Soros Foundation File, 1991-1994. (Box 5)
  Correspondence, financial records, and files on projects in Central and Eastern Europe and Russia reflecting the foundation's policy of promoting openness in societies, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Correspondence, 1991-1994. (Folder 5: 1)
  - Financial records, 1991. (Folder 5: 2)
  - Project file, 1991-1993.
    - Albania, Belarus, Bulgaria, Crimea, Croatia, Estonia, Hungary, Kazakhstan and Kyrgyzsia, and Moldavia (Folder 5: 3)
    - Romania, Soviet Union, Slovenia, and Yugoslavia (Folder 5: 4)
- File on Organizations, 1991-1995. (Box 5-6)
  Clippings and printed matter, correspondence, itinerary, memoranda, notes, press release, proposal, report, speech, and statement, relating to activities of organizations promoting democracy, human rights, and independent media, arranged alphabetically by organization name
  - General
    - Czech Republic, 1994. (Folder 5: 5)
    - Macedonia, 1994-1995. (Folder 5: 6-12)
    - Miscellany (Folder 5: 13)
  - Baltic Media Center, n.d. (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Council of Europe, 1991-1993. (Folder 6: 2)
  - Helsinki Watch, 1993. (Folder 6: 3)
  - Independent Journalism Foundation, n.d. (Folder 6: 4)
  - Independent Media in Europe, n.d. (Folder 6: 5-6)
  - Institute for Constitutional and Legislative Policy: The Central European University, 1993. (Folder 6: 7)
  - Institute for Democracy in Eastern Europe, 1995. (Folder 6: 8)
  - International Society for Human Rights (ISHR), 1993. (Folder 6: 9)
  - National Forum Foundation, n.d. (Folder 6: 10)
  - U.S. Agency for International Development, 1995 (Folder 6: 11)
- Computer Disk, 1995. (Box 6)
  One 3.5-inch, 2 MB computer disk containing six documents. All documents are versions of "Guidelines for 1995 Phare and Tacis Democracy Programme" in various languages and file formats, which have been printed and filed in this series
  - One 3.5 inch, 2 MB computer disk (Folder 6: 12)
  - "Guidelines for 1995 Phare and Tacis Democracy Programme," 1995., See also box 3 (Folder 6: 13-14)
    Documents printed from computer disk.